<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[EWuasDigitalResearchGarden]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>https://emilrugenstein.github.io/EWuasDigitalResearchGardenExport/</link><image><url>https://emilrugenstein.github.io/EWuasDigitalResearchGardenExport/lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>EWuasDigitalResearchGarden</title><link>https://emilrugenstein.github.io/EWuasDigitalResearchGardenExport/</link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 14:43:38 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://emilrugenstein.github.io/EWuasDigitalResearchGardenExport/lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 14:43:38 GMT</pubDate><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator/><item><title><![CDATA[G1 Chango Lo Che]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Chango Lo Che
<br>Player size: 5-10
<br>Age: 5-13
<br>Sex: Both
<br>Duration: 10-20
<br>Occasion: exercise
<br>Category: ball, exercise
<br>Traditional: somewhat
<br>Material needed: ball
<br>Mechanics: player elimination, real time
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: Chango Lo Che means "new pass". This is not a Maa name but that is the name they children use.
<br>History: It's not a traditional game but it has been around for at least 40 years. The kids learn it mostly at school
<br>Usage: Played often in the school yard in Mile 46
<br>Information retrieval: 

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Senewa Maison" href="\persons\senewa-maison.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Senewa Maison</a> on the <a data-href="10-11-2024" href="\10-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">10-11-2024</a> and this is her favourite game
<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> remembers this game from his school time


<br><br>
<br>started by two players standing in opposite side and the other players at the middle of the field
<br>the two outside players throw the ball onto the players in the middle after each other and try to hit them
<br>the players in the middle therefore run each time to the opposite side of the throwing outside player
<br>if someone is hit he or she is out of the game
<br>if only one person remains in the middle, the two outside players will try for 5 more times (they often count down loudly), if the middle person survives this her or she is the winner
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain

<br><img alt="G1Drawing.jpg" src="\games\attachments\g1drawing.jpg"> Two outside player, which try to hit the middle players with a ball


<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g1-chango-lo-che.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G1 Chango Lo Che.md</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 15:01:29 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="games\attachments\g1drawing.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="games\attachments\g1drawing.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[G2 Osurruo]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Osurruo
<br>Player size: 2-4
<br>Age: 6-15
<br>Sex: Both
<br>Duration: 10-30
<br>Occasion: leisure
<br>Category: mental, dexterity
<br>Traditional: yes
<br>Material needed: stones (1 main stone for each player and 12 additional stones)
<br>Mechanics: pattern building, real time, dexterity
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: no particular meaning, but the main stone of each player is called "Olmenye" which means father in Maa
<br>History: Old game that is played by Masaai for at least several generations
<br>Usage: It is still very liked among kids and often played in school breaks. It is also liked for leisure occasions as it does not require much movement.
<br>Information retrieval: 

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Senewa Maison" href="\persons\senewa-maison.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Senewa Maison</a> on the <a data-href="10-11-2024" href="\10-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">10-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>Each player has one main stone called "Olmenye" (father in Maa) this has to be thrown and catched as the player removes or returns the other 12 stones (called cows) into a hole
<br>The players rotate usually clockwise. One player starts and the others watch if he or she plays right. What matters is that the playing player returns the stones in the right manner.
<br>At the start the main stone is thrown in the air and all other 12 stones have to be removed out of the hole before the Olmenye is catched again.
<br>Afterwards 1 stone has to be returned for each time the Olmenye is thrown into the air. Only the same hand can be used for all this!
<br>Then all stones are removed again (with the same hand during another throw of the Olmenye) and the player has to return 2 each at once until finishing all 12.
<br>This is then continued with returning 3 each, then 4 each, until all 12 are returned at once. If a round number is not dividing 12 evenly the remaining stones will just be put in at once afterwards. Meaning that in round 5 the player has to return 5 stones each and then return the remaining 2 stones afterwards at once. The same for e.g. round 7, first he or she has to return 7 stones and then the remaining 5 stones at once.
<br>The player wins, who manages in his or her turn to do the correct return pattern up to round 12 and does not lose the Olmenye in between.
<br>The winner can then optionally select one of the remaining players and say "Ai shoo enkerai" (I gave you a child) and that selected player can then start trying again. The rotation continues without the winner.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain

<br><img alt="G2Drawing.jpg" src="\games\attachments\g2drawing.jpg"> Every player has a Olmenye (father) stone. The 12 cow stones are in the middle. Only one is playing at a time.


<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g2-osurruo.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G2 Osurruo.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 13:28:38 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="games\attachments\g2drawing.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="games\attachments\g2drawing.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[G3 Olbanto]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Olbanto
<br>Player size: 3-6
<br>Age: 6-15
<br>Sex: Both
<br>Duration: 2-30
<br>Occasion: leisure
<br>Category: dexterity
<br>Traditional: no
<br>Material needed: each player needs 1 small and round fruit or ball 
<br>Mechanics: pick-up and deliver, dexterity, variable player order
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: Olbanto is Maa and means "something small and round". In English or Swahili the game is called banto (with a soft t)
<br>History: It is more modern and small yellow and round fruits are used (called "Intulele" in Maa and "solanum incanum" as botanical name) or kids in town can buy small and round balls which are sold in shops and called bands or bantos. They are cheap and accessible and can usually be bought for 5 Ksh.
<br>Usage: Played often by kids and the bantos can be bought in shops
<br>Information retrieval:

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Senewa Maison" href="\persons\senewa-maison.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Senewa Maison</a> on the <a data-href="12-11-2024" href="\12-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">12-11-2024</a>


<br><br>
<br>Players start at a line which is around 2 meters away from hole. 
<br>The goal is to get the balls into that hole. For that the players start after each other to throw/roll the ball towards the hole.
<br>If nobody manages to get into the hole the players start where their ball stopped last time in the order based on how close they were to the hole (the closest one can go first)
<br>The winner is the one who reaches into the hole first. 
<br>Often this game is repeated many rounds and the wins of each player are counted. 
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain

<br><img alt="G3Drawing.jpg" src="\games\attachments\g3drawing.jpg"> Players start at a line to throw their bantos. The winner is the one who reaches the hole first.


<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g3-olbanto.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G3 Olbanto.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 13:33:51 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="games\attachments\g3drawing.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="games\attachments\g3drawing.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[G4 Ntapipiyio]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Ntapipiyio
<br>Player size: 4+
<br>Age: 5-13
<br>Sex: Both
<br>Duration: 10-20 (depends heavily on player size)
<br>Occasion: leisure
<br>Category: singing, sitting
<br>Traditional: yes
<br>Material needed: - 
<br>Mechanics: player elimination, fixed pattern/ pattern building
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: ? (probably a Maa word)
<br>History: traditionally played with the same passed-on song
<br>Usage: often especially when children sit around and rest
<br>Information retrieval: 

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Neng'arua ole Mukunti" href="\persons\neng'arua-ole-mukunti.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Neng'arua ole Mukunti</a> on the <a data-href="13-11-2024" href="\13-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">13-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>Players sit down in one line with stretched legs forward.
<br>One main player sings the game song and taps each foot after each other with every syllable.
<br>When the song is over the last foot he touched has to be removed (bend).
<br>If one player got removed his or her two legs that player is out, but still sits with both legs bended 
<br>The tapping goes back and forth while the song is sung and bended legs are skipped
<br>The song goes as follows: 

<br>"Ntapipiyio ntapipiyio aa muntara rinta aa dede dede dede pae,<br>
aarintaa rinta ngurme aa ngurme ngurme tenkeria" 
<br>"Tenkeria" means end and is sung and tapped as one


<br>The player who remains last with one or two stretched legs wins:
<br>The game is often repeated multiple times.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain

<br>


<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g4-ntapipiyio.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G4 Ntapipiyio.md</guid><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 10:48:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[G5 Osuyiet]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Osuyiet (Bow and Arrows practice)
<br>Player size: 5-20
<br>Age: 20-40
<br>Sex: male
<br>Duration: 3-5 hours
<br>Occasion: exercise
<br>Category: sport
<br>Traditional: yes
<br>Material needed: weapons
<br>Mechanics: dexterity
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: Osuyiet is a Maa word and refers to the head of the arrow.
<br>History: Traditionally the Maasai would practice a lot with arrow and bow and use it to shoot wild animals or to fight other sections or tribes. Today however, it is of less relevance due to the wild life protection regulations and the fact that tensions are usually managed to be settled by negotiations (often with government help).
<br>Usage: It is still practiced today, but significantly less, and only far away from the settlements like Mile 46. Sometimes young boys also build their own bows and try to practice by themselves.
<br>Information retrieval:

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Lapiyioi ole Mampurre" href="\persons\lapiyioi-ole-mampurre.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Lapiyioi ole Mampurre</a> on the <a data-href="13-11-2024" href="\13-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">13-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>Bow and arrow practice where the players try to aim at something from near or far.
<br>The player with the best aim wins.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain
<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g5-osuyiet.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G5 Osuyiet.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 14:57:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[G6 Enkeshi]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Enkeshi
<br>Player size: 2-6
<br>Age: 30+
<br>Sex: male
<br>Duration: 30-90
<br>Occasion: mental competition
<br>Category: board game
<br>Traditional: yes
<br>Material needed: 1 Enkeshi board (with 2 times 8 holes) and 48 stones
<br>Mechanics: pick-up and deliver, deck/bag building, area control, grid/area movement, pattern building
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: "Enkeshi (pl. Inkeshi)" comes from the Maa word "Enkesha" which means to compete. The stones are called "Inkishu" (meaning cows), possibly the name could also come from that. 
<br>History: 

<br>This is a very traditional game, which is for men only, but the story goes that a widowed woman introduced this game first to the Maasai men. It is said that the widow still had many cows, but no one to assist her with the cow deliveries of new calves. Because of that she taught this game to men so that they stay at her home. When the cows gave birth she could ask the playing men who were around to assist.
<br>Traditionally this game is only for Maasai men after they underwent their last big ceremony, the "Olngesher". In this ceremony the left and right hand groups are joined together. The left hand group is a bit younger and has to "catch up" to the right hand group. See more here:  <a data-href="Describtion#Maasai age groups" href="\describtion.html#Maasai_age_groups" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Describtion &gt; Maasai age groups</a> While it was thus only allowed for the 5th and last age group to play the game, younger men would sometimes still build and play it in the sand while herding cattle.
<br>The board is traditionally made from a special tree called Olng'osua by proper carving men.


<br>Usage: Nowadays it is played less and less and only some people still know how to play it. But it used to be very famous before. The game has two sides with 1:1 as a default, but it is often played in teams as well (e.g. 2:2 or 3:3).
<br>Information retrieval: 

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Lapiyioi ole Mampurre" href="\persons\lapiyioi-ole-mampurre.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Lapiyioi ole Mampurre</a> on the <a data-href="13-11-2024" href="\13-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">13-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>The board has 8 holes on each sided and the game is played in two opposing teams.
<br>For the beginning each side puts 4 stones in each of the 6 holes on the right hand and the two left holes are left empty.
<br>One side starts by grabbing all the 4 stones from one hole on their side and continues anti-clockwise by putting the stones from the hand back into the wholes one each until the last stone is from the hand is put
<br>If in that hole there are other stones, all stones from that hole are grapped and the previous step is repeated.
<br>This is continued until a hole with no stones is reached with a last stone from the hand. 
<br>The first round of this is especially important as the first end points determine the bank of each side. These two stones in the holes were only one stone remains are called "Olker" (meaning male sheep) and they become the bank of the corresponding side. The bank is called "Emoti" (meaning pot).
<br>Afterwards the players continue in the same manner but now they can start from any hole - expect the bank hole of the other side
<br>The game ends when no movements can be done anymore. This happens when no other hole, besides the two bank holes, has enough stones to reach the next hole.
<br>Now, the stones in the two banks are counted and the side with the most stones wins.
<br>The rules of this game may seem simple, but the dynamics and strategies can quickly become sophisticated.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain

<br><img alt="G6DrawingStart.jpg" src="\games\attachments\g6drawingstart.jpg"> Start position of the game. The Enkeshi is played counter-clockwise.


<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g6-enkeshi.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G6 Enkeshi.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 15:00:45 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="games\attachments\g6drawingstart.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="games\attachments\g6drawingstart.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[G7 Enkukuo]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Enkukuo
<br>Player size: 4+
<br>Age: 7-14
<br>Sex: both
<br>Duration: 5-15
<br>Occasion: leisure
<br>Category: mental
<br>Traditional: yes
<br>Material needed: a small piece of charcoal 
<br>Mechanics: acting, scenario driven
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: "Enkukuo" is a Maa word and means charcoal, but can also mean voting
<br>History: This game is very traditional and also has a lot engrained Maasai culture in it. For example, the seven stages through which the teams have to go through are also descriptive of what is important in Maasai culture. They are meant to remind people of good development - from a bad state of dirty water to entering a good house with a good environment. See the instructions for the seven stages. 
<br>Usage: It is usually played at night at around 9 p.m. until midnight. There is a believe that when played during the day, livestock will be lost. The game can also be used to teach children about the importance of caring about the environment as the seven stages characterise a positive development 
<br>Information retrieval: 

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Rimanto Mukunti" href="\persons\rimanto-mukunti.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rimanto Mukunti</a> on the <a data-href="13-11-2024" href="\13-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">13-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>The game is played in two teams, which usually give themselves a name of a Maasai clan (one Maasai section has usually many clans) or of one of the five Maasai age group or any other name
<br>The game will be started by the group who prepared the charcoal, as usually the coal has to be fresh from a burning fire place and cooled down by water or saliva
<br>One person from that team will start by pretending to place the small charcoal on the palms of his teammates, who close their hands to fists right after. 
<br>After this, the other team has to nominate one person, who has to guess the person who has the charcoal. Even the person who was pretending to give the charcoal still could have it in one of his or her fists. 
<br>Normally, it is enough to guess the right person, but sometimes when only few players play this game the correct hand has to be guessed as well. 
<br>The tension of this game often makes smaller kids laugh and this can be used as indication, who has the charcoal.
<br>If the location of the charcoal was guessed correctly it is the other's team turn and that team gets one point. If not the same team starts again with "distributing" the charcoal amongst them and they get a point.
<br>The game is played until one team gets seven points. The seventh point is usually referred to as "entering the house"
<br>The 7 point stages of the game are called: 

<br>"Enkare neingole ilasho" (the water that is spoiled calves) 
<br>"Enkare nasila" (the clean water)
<br>"Nasheta ematua nabo" (the building with one side)
<br>"Nasheta imatuan arre" (the building with two sides) 
<br>"Nasheta imatuan uni" (the building with thre sides) 
<br>"Emparnat olerai" (the complete permanent house) 
<br>"Aajing aji" (entering the house) -&gt; this is the winning stage 


<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain
<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g7-enkukuo.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G7 Enkukuo.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 15:02:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[G8 Olenkiserpep]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Olenkiserpep
<br>Player size: 2-15
<br>Age: 10-25
<br>Sex: male
<br>Duration: 30-60
<br>Occasion: exercise
<br>Category: throwing, dexterity
<br>Traditional: yes
<br>Material needed: 1 stick per player 
<br>Mechanics: dexterity, scenario driven
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: "Olenkiserpep" is a Maa word and describes the sound and action of the sliding sticks.
<br>History: 

<br>This game is very traditionally and used as a way of approaching girls, by competing for them and teasing them if one has "won" a particular girl. Traditionally only girls from other clans can be considered for a marriage, but this is ignored for this game as it is only playing with potential relationships. Still, after the game the players often approach the ladies who they won and sometimes relationships start from it.
<br>The sticks to play with are traditionally from a shrub called "Ositeti" (Grewia Bicolor) and have to be very straight. Each young man should have his own stick.


<br>Usage: It is still very much played nowadays by young boys in the same manner.
<br>Information retrieval:

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Joshua Kimirei Mayiasek" href="\persons\joshua-kimirei-mayiasek.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Joshua Kimirei Mayiasek</a> on the <a data-href="14-11-2024" href="\14-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">14-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>The game should take place on a straight road or field and can be started by any player from the starting line which is previously drawn into the sand.
<br>The players will slide their stick in a straight manner forward, with the goal to slide as far as possible. The stick has to touch the ground at the starting line, otherwise the throw does not count.
<br>For each round the players decide for a name of a girl of similar or younger age which they now. The round is then about this girl.
<br>The player who slided the furthest wins the round and thereby also the girl.
<br>This repeated until the players decided to end it or until one player reaches a previously agreed number of girls.
<br>The player who "won" the most girls, wins. 
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain

<br><img alt="G8Drawing.jpg" src="\games\attachments\g8drawing.jpg">


<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g8-olenkiserpep.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G8 Olenkiserpep.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 15:03:59 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="games\attachments\g8drawing.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="games\attachments\g8drawing.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[G9 Eepa]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Eepa (Wrestling)
<br>Player size: 2+
<br>Age: 10-35
<br>Sex: male
<br>Duration: 10+
<br>Occasion: exercise
<br>Category: fighting
<br>Traditional: yes
<br>Material needed: -
<br>Mechanics: dexterity
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: The name "Eepa" is Maa and means trying.
<br>History: This game is traditionally used to determine among the warrior (Morran) age group who is the strongest. It is also a way to impress women and often played by smaller boys as well, who aspire to become like a Morran.
<br>Usage: Traditonally there were also big competitions between different villages and sections, but nowadays it is only played locally (in the Ewuas area).
<br>Information retrieval:

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Joshua Kimirei Mayiasek" href="\persons\joshua-kimirei-mayiasek.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Joshua Kimirei Mayiasek</a> on the <a data-href="14-11-2024" href="\14-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">14-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>It's a one versus one wrestling game, without weapons on a open and sandy field.
<br>The player wins who manages to put the other one down a certain amount of times (which have to be agreed upon before the game starts)
<br>The player change in a manner that in the end the strongest one is determined.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain
<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g9-eepa.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G9 Eepa.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 15:04:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[G10 Kupepeta]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Kupepeta
<br>Player size: 2-6
<br>Age: 7-14
<br>Sex: male
<br>Duration: 10+
<br>Occasion: exercise
<br>Category: ball game
<br>Traditional: somewhat
<br>Material needed: 1 ball
<br>Mechanics: dexterity, set collection, POINT COLLECTION
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: Kupepeta is a Kiswahili word and originally refers to the process of separating grain from chaff by throwing it into the air and letting the wind blow away the lighter chaff. 
<br>History: It was already played 40 years ago, but is not a traditional game.
<br>Usage: The game is played by young boys, who often use a self-made ball.
<br>Information retrieval:

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="David Kerore" href="\persons\david-kerore.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">David Kerore</a> on the <a data-href="15-11-2024" href="\15-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">15-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>The first player starts to kick the ball into the air and then bumps the ball repeatedly with the same leg.
<br>Each bounce is counted loudly and the player has to stop when the ball touches the ground.
<br>The number of bounces will then be added to the score of that player and its the next player's turn.
<br>The scores are written and changed into the sand as a table with either numbers or the initials of the players as header and their score below. After each turn the score of that player will be updated accoridingly.
<br>The players decide when to end the game, but then the player with the highest total score wins.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain

<br><img alt="G10DrawingStart.jpg" src="\games\attachments\g10drawingstart.jpg"> Table with scores which usually drawn into the sand


<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g10-kupepeta.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G10 Kupepeta.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 15:06:25 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="games\attachments\g10drawingstart.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="games\attachments\g10drawingstart.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[G11 Ready]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Ready (before it was called Koipima)
<br>Player size: 2+
<br>Age: 5-13
<br>Sex: both
<br>Duration: 5+
<br>Occasion: exercise
<br>Category: jumping
<br>Traditional: somewhat
<br>Material needed: 1 stone
<br>Mechanics: dexterity, pattern building
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: Now it is just an English word, but it used to be called "Koipima" (Maa for measured)
<br>History: new game
<br>Usage: encountered on the school yard during breaks
<br>Information retrieval:

<br>encountered by <a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> and <a data-href="Emil Rugenstein" href="\persons\emil-rugenstein.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Emil Rugenstein</a> when they visited EWuas primary school on the <a data-href="09-07-2025" href="\09-07-2025" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">09-07-2025</a>
<br>also mentioned by <a data-href="David Kerore" href="\persons\david-kerore.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">David Kerore</a> when <a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed him on the <a data-href="15-11-2024" href="\15-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">15-11-2024</a>


<br><br>
<br>A field of 2 x 5 rectangles is drawn. With the last field on each side being longer than the other ones.
<br>Then one player starts by throwing a stone into the first rectangle on one side.
<br>Now the player has to jump into that tile and kick the stone on one leg only into the next rectangle until he or she reaches the end and then has to come back on the other side. The player has two jump on leg but can rest and put both legs down in the longer rectangles at the end.
<br>During this the stone cannot move further than one rectangle at a time and also the feet of the jumping player are not allowed to touch the lines. If this happens an outside player screams "banned" and the next player can try.
<br>If a player finishes the first round, he or she now has two throw the stone into the second rectangle, jump to that rectangle and then start from there again. 
<br>This is then continued until the 5th rectangle and then backwards on the other side. 
<br>It rarely happens that a player finishes all stages.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain

<br><img alt="G11Drawing.jpg" src="\games\attachments\g11drawing.jpg"> Outline of the game plan.


<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 

<br><img alt="G11ImpressionEwuas.jpg" src="\games\attachments\g11impressionewuas.jpg">Playing children at EWuas primary. One plays and the others watch if she does it correctly


]]></description><link>games\g11-ready.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G11 Ready.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 13:06:06 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="games\attachments\g11drawing.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="games\attachments\g11drawing.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[G12 Mahewa]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Mahewa
<br>Player size: 2+
<br>Age: 7-15
<br>Sex: male
<br>Duration: 10+
<br>Occasion: exercise
<br>Category: sport
<br>Traditional: no
<br>Material needed: soft sand to land and something to jump from
<br>Mechanics: dexterity
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: Mahewa is a Kiswahili word and refers to the air
<br>History: This is not a traditional game and came up only recently in Ewuas
<br>Usage: It is played by young boys to compete, impress and have fun.
<br>Information retrieval:

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="David Masharia" href="\persons\david-masharia.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">David Masharia</a> on the <a data-href="15-11-2024" href="\15-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">15-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>The players will prepare a somewhat soft and sandy landing space and then jump from a heightened point like a pile of tubes or a cement back.
<br>The goal to do impressive flips.
<br>If one player fails his jump the others will laugh, but they are also supportive and teach each other.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain
<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g12-mahewa.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G12 Mahewa.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 13:05:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[G13 Draft]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Draft
<br>Player size: 2
<br>Age: 10+
<br>Sex: (mostly) male 
<br>Duration: 10-30
<br>Occasion: mental competition
<br>Category: board game
<br>Traditional: no
<br>Material needed: draft board and stones
<br>Mechanics: 
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: English word
<br>History: The game was introduced in 1990 by a Kikuyu man known as Wakairore in Mile 46 town
<br>Usage: In Mile 46 is a group of 10-15 men (age 40-60) who are very interested and almost every day and the game is also beyond that known and liked
<br>Information retrieval:

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Mosiampo Leyian" href="\persons\mosiampo-leyian.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Mosiampo Leyian</a> on the <a data-href="19-11-2024" href="\19-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">19-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>Normal draft, but it is often played repeatedly and it happens that the counts of the last competition are remembered.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain
<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g13-draft.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G13 Draft.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 14:31:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[G14 Oltingilo]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Oltingilo (Rounder)
<br>Player size: 5+
<br>Age: 5-14
<br>Sex: both
<br>Duration: 5-15
<br>Occasion: exercise
<br>Category: sport
<br>Traditional: somewhat
<br>Material needed: -
<br>Mechanics: rondels, player elimination, dexterity
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation: Oltingilo is the Maa word for the game and refers to the rounds the player make. In English this game is called rounder.
<br>History: It's a traditional game, that has a traditional song to it that is sung while playing it and originally also involved kids trying to escape from the middle of the circle. However, the game seems to have evolved and it is now played in a simpler version.
<br>Usage: It is still played when many children come together for example in the school break.
<br>Information retrieval:

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Jane Shapashina" href="\persons\jane-shapashina.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Jane Shapashina</a> on the <a data-href="20-11-2024" href="\20-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">20-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>The game is started by all players (e.g. the whole class of students) making a circle by holding hands.
<br>Then everyone runs clockwise as they sing "Oltingilo, oltingilo, ..." or "Rounder, rounder, ..." 
<br>The players start running slowly, but then become faster and faster.
<br>When one player falls down, he or she is out and has to leave the circle. 
<br>This is continued until only two players remain - they are then the winners.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain
<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g14-oltingilo.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G14 Oltingilo.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 14:11:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[G15 Sand Filling Bottle]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name: Sand Filling Bottle Game
<br>Player size: 3
<br>Age: 5-11
<br>Sex: both
<br>Duration: 5
<br>Occasion: exercise
<br>Category: ball game
<br>Traditional: no
<br>Material needed: 1 ball, 1 empty bottle, and sand
<br>Mechanics: real time, dexterity
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation (if applicable): -
<br>History: It has been around for a while but is not a real traditional game
<br>Usage: especially played by the small kids in primary school, but also older kids
<br>Information retrieval:

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed <a data-href="Jane Shapashina" href="\persons\jane-shapashina.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Jane Shapashina</a> on the <a data-href="20-11-2024" href="\20-11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">20-11-2024</a> 


<br><br>
<br>One player has to fill a bottle with sand, while the other two players try to hit that player with a ball from a certain distance and opposing sides. 
<br>Only one ball is used and the main player wins if he or she manages to fill the bottle with sand without being hit by the ball from the other two players.
<br>The game is often repeated many times and has an interesting component of time pressure which makes it fun to play.
<br><br>
<br>graphic to explain
<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\g15-sand-filling-bottle.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/G15 Sand Filling Bottle.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 14:11:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[X_Game_Template]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
<br>Name:
<br>Player size:
<br>Age:
<br>Sex:
<br>Duration:
<br>Occasion: education/ exercise/ leisure
<br>Category: Ball game/ board game/ ...
<br>Traditional: yes/ somewhat/ no
<br>Material needed: Ball/ sticks/ stones/ board/ ...
<br>Mechanics: 
<br><br>
<br>Name explanation (if applicable):
<br>History: e.g. how traditional it is, where it comes from etc
<br>Usage: how often it is played and known
<br>Information retrieval:

<br><a data-href="Ezekiel Roimen" href="\persons\ezekiel-roimen.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ezekiel Roimen</a> interviewed [[]] on the <a data-href="11-2024" href="\11-2024" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">11-2024</a> 


<br><br><br>
<br>graphic to explain
<br>photos and videos with small descriptions 
]]></description><link>games\x_game_template.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Games/X_Game_Template.md</guid><pubDate>Fri, 11 Jul 2025 14:56:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Describtion]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>
<br><a data-href="G1 Chango Lo Che" href="\games\g1-chango-lo-che.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G1 Chango Lo Che</a>
<br><a data-href="G2 Osurruo" href="\games\g2-osurruo.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G2 Osurruo</a>
<br><a data-href="G3 Olbanto" href="\games\g3-olbanto.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G3 Olbanto</a>
<br><a data-href="G4 Ntapipiyio" href="\games\g4-ntapipiyio.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G4 Ntapipiyio</a>
<br><a data-href="G5 Osuyiet" href="\games\g5-osuyiet.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G5 Osuyiet</a>
<br><a data-href="G6 Enkeshi" href="\games\g6-enkeshi.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G6 Enkeshi</a>
<br><a data-href="G7 Enkukuo" href="\games\g7-enkukuo.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G7 Enkukuo</a>
<br><a data-href="G8 Olenkiserpep" href="\games\g8-olenkiserpep.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G8 Olenkiserpep</a>
<br><a data-href="G9 Eepa" href="\games\g9-eepa.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G9 Eepa</a>
<br><a data-href="G10 Kupepeta" href="\games\g10-kupepeta.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G10 Kupepeta</a>
<br><a data-href="G11 Ready" href="\games\g11-ready.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G11 Ready</a>
<br><a data-href="G12 Mahewa" href="\games\g12-mahewa.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G12 Mahewa</a>
<br><a data-href="G13 Draft" href="\games\g13-draft.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G13 Draft</a>
<br><a data-href="G14 Oltingilo" href="\games\g14-oltingilo.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G14 Oltingilo</a>
<br><a data-href="G15 Sand Filling Bottle" href="\games\g15-sand-filling-bottle.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">G15 Sand Filling Bottle</a>
<br><br><br>
<br>Young ones 

<br>Inkipaata -&gt; circumcision as transition to next group (newly circumcised)

<br>traditionally with around 20 years, but nowadays often done earlier




<br>Newly circumcised

<br>Shaving ceremony as transition to next group

<br>nowadays boys can decide if the go back to school afterwards or the become a real Morang




<br>Warriors (Morran)

<br>Climax of Maasai live
<br>The often grow their hair very long
<br>Another very big ceremony (called "Eunoto") which ends the Morran-Ship


<br>Young elders 

<br>Last ceremony is the "Olngesher" where the younger left hand group and the right hand group are joined together as one cohort


<br>Elders
]]></description><link>describtion.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Describtion.md</guid><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 14:56:34 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>